<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The manifest, or declaration of His Sacred Imperial Maiesty Translated out of Latin.</title>
            <author>Ferdinand II, Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00674</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850250</idno>
  <idno type="VID">15439</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240872442</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10809</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S115030</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99850250e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The manifest, or declaration of His Sacred Imperial Maiesty Translated out of Latin.</title>
                  <author>Ferdinand II, Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted with Licence, M. DC. XX [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Bohemia(Czechoslovakis) --  History --  1526-  --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15439:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15439:1"/>
            <p>THE MANIFEST, OR DECLARATION OF HIS SACRED IMPERIALL MAIESTY. <hi>Translated out of Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted with Licence, M. DC. XX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15439:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15439:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ERDINAND the Second, by the grace of God elected Emperour of the Romans, euer Augustus, King of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Hungary, Bohemia, Dalmatia, Croatia, and Sclauonia &amp;c. Archduke of Austria, Duke of Burgundy, Styria, Carinthia, Carniola, and Wittem berge &amp;c. Earle of Tirolle &amp;c. To all Soueraigne Kinges, our Breethren, &amp; most deare Cosens, wisheth increase of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, mutuall Loue and happy Prosperity. As also to all and singular Princes, as well Ecclesiasticall, as Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Electors, Archbishops, Bishops, Earles, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Captains, Lieutenants, Standard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers, Powers, Burgemaisters, Consuls: and to all the Magistrats of all, and euery of our Countryes, Cittyes, Houlds and Communityes; withall the rest of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and most deare subiectes of all, and euery of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Health, our Imperiall Fauour, and increase of al Felicity &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Although we doubt not, but that it is notorious and manifest vnto all persons, as well within, as without the bounds and limits of our Sacred Roman Empyre, what miserable slaughter, calamity, and desolation hath inuironed our kingdome of Bohemia, a noble and most renowned part belonging to the body of our Imperiall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15439:3"/> Crowne, and chiefe amongst our secular Electorships, togeather with our hereditary Prouinces that border and adioyne vnto it; and what an inundation of misery, the vntimely and deplorable necessity of this new raysed war hath brought vpon our harmlesse subiects, togeather with the vniuersall ruine of our dearest Country: yet haue we thought it not vnworthy our labour to lay downe the origen, successe, and causes of this mournefull Tragedy; chiefly to the end that the sinister and maleuolent calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations, and false pretences of fraudulent, and lying tongues being detected, and simple truth stript naked from the ragges of all imposture &amp; false suspition, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with she hath maliciously beene cloathed, may appeare to all men more conspicuous and manifest.</p>
            <p>The first source and fountaine therefore of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable rebellion, or at least the sad tyme when it first brake forth to publike, and like a swelling riuer that hath ouerflowne the bankes, by which it was restrayned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to powre it selfe with wast and desolation to our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable Countrey, was in the raigne of our dread Lord, deare Vncle, &amp; most respected Father MATTHIAS, of happy memory, late Roman Emperour, King of Hungary and Bohemia &amp;c. at what tyme some of our Bohemian States, vnder pretence of I know not what agrieuances, wherein they alleadged the priuiledges of Religion, and that which is called the Regal, or Maiestall Charter, to be infringed and violated; did in most headdy and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous manner, breake into our Castle and Royall Chancery, layd violent handes vpon men of prime qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, being the Magistrates, Lieutenants, and chiefe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putyes of absent Caesar, their vndoubted Lord and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15439:3"/> Soueraigne; and with a barbarous, cruell, and which to all posterity will be esteemed a most temerarious and infamous example, without examining their cause, or hearing their iust defence, did in a fit of brainsicke fury throw them downe headlong from the tops of highest windowes; and then adding to Rashnesse Obstinacy, that they might desperatly defend what they had wickedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, they brake into open armes, and without al respect vnto their absent Soueraigne, deposed from their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and place, not only the foresayd Officers, now lying breathlesse &amp; halfe dead vpon the hurt and perill of their falls; but all others also throughout the Territoryes of that Kingdome and Dominion. And not content heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with iniuriously inuaded the Royalties of that Crowne, which from all memorie of men, had formerly beene accounted sacred and inuiolable, changed all the auncient forme and frame of gouernment into a new, wherof they would needs create and stile themselues, forsooth, Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours; exceeding so haynously both in the manner and measure the limits of moderate defending their Religion (if by the tenour of the aforesayd Regall Charter, they haue any right at all to such an Action, when no cause of Religion with any colour of probability can be proued to be questioned) that euen by these audacious facts of theirs it is apparent vnto all that are not willfully hood winked with partiality, that these sinnefull, precipitious, &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous attempts of disloyall subiects against the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of their Leige Lord, cannot, nor ought not to be mentioned, or styled by any other title thē by the proper names of Seditious, Rebellious, and Execrable Treasons.</p>
            <p>It is not now our purpose to examine with what foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15439:4"/> or ground of reason those agrieuances can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched and maintained, that are comprized, diuulged &amp; published in the Bohemian Apologies, extant vnder the name of one part of the States of that Kingdome (though they would seeme to be vnder the names of both,) or how far the pretended offences of priuate persons should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound vnto the preiudice and iniury of supreme publike Magistrats; neither is it our part to extenuate or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn those errors (if perhaps any were committed) before we tooke into our hands the raynes of Royall Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for that (if any such were) they happened wholy without all fault of ours, and therfore the blame thereof ought not in equity and iustice to be deriued and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to vs. But we are hopefully perswaded that euery faithfull Cittizen that is inclinable to peace, and an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent friend to equity and iustice, when he shall impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially consider the proceedings hitherto continued and held on; and not being swayed with preiudice &amp; passion shall indifferently peruse the Treatises and Informations which haue byn heertofore printed about this businesse; wil euidētly perceaue that to these pretended agrieuances (whatsoeuer in themselues they might be) a more calme and seasonable, or at the least a lesse turbulent and sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious remedy should haue byn applied and thought vpon. Neither was it therefore conuenient for them, like rabide Children, to pull vpon themselues the ruine of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and as it were to constraine the lawfull Magistrate to suppresse iniury with violence, &amp; draw that sword which God hath put into his hands, to the iust reuenge and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of rebellious malefactors.</p>
            <p>For truly if these controuersies which arose vpon the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15439:4"/> priuiledge of free exercise of their religion, could not haue byn decided &amp; extinguished by those very meanes, which their forementioned Charter doth peculiarly prescribe, that is, by some indifferent Arbiters, frankly deputed by the States of either Religion; &amp; that also were true which euery where they publish, and with earnest endeauours striue to possesse the world with the opinion of, to wit, that they were vtterly debarred from all accesse vnto the presence of their Royall Soueraigne; yet who is there that can doubt, that in a case of such distresse and difficulty, the Princes Electours of the sacred Roman Empire, moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with pittifull cōpassion of their lamentable distresses, would either of their owne accord haue interposed effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually their intercessiō; or inuited therto by the intreaties and complaints of the oppressed party, would for their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed sollicitude and wonted prouidence, haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently preuented such extremes, as might precipitate the one side into headlong despaire, or driue the other to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced necessity.</p>
            <p>But after these wicked Rebelles had neglected al sweet meanes of remedy, and it had pleased the new appointed Directours, and their Complices to combine themselues in a most bloudy conspiracy, that by audacious cruelty they might surprize the hartes of our beloued subiects, and wholy possesse them with fearfull thoughts of terror and amazement, thinking thereby to intangle others in the participation of their sinfull treachery; they placed the hope of their impunity in armes, &amp; sought to bolster their wicked designes, vnder the colour &amp; cloake of the name &amp; authority of our States. Wherfore the Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty of Caesar our deare deceased Lord, could do no lesse
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15439:5"/> in duty then prouide, although it were with armed hand, that which he thought expedient for the defence &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his Royall Authority and Kingly iurisdiction; especially finding in these obstinate delinquents no place for obedience and Fatherly admonition, no hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, no inclination to lend a willing eare to better counsells; but the contagion, like to a festering sore and noisome canker, euery day dispersing it self to the greater infection and detriment of the Weale publicke, to diffuse also its venomous contagion, to the destruction of the neighbouring Prouinces: but yet before he suffered the forces he had leuied to breake forth to open violence, in iust commiseration of his subiects heauy calamities, he did omit no carefull diligence by sweet meanes to appease the stormes of this inraged tempest. He committed therefore the composing thereof equally vnto the care &amp; prudent moderation of the prime Electours of this sacred Empire, omitting no diligence that might conduce vnto the speedy and effectual pacifying of exasperated mindes, &amp; laying downe of armes; although this latter desire of his found many delaies and vnexpected obstacles. But how coldly &amp; backwardly his Bohemian subiects did answere to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward propension, and with what impertinent conditions they laboured to disturbe and trauerse his holy purposes, their articles &amp; informations yet extant in print do beare aboundant record.</p>
            <p>In the meane tyme Caesar deceasing, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Bohemia, with the vnited Prouinces, by vertue of our Royall Coronation, and the Homage, and Fealty in former tyme solemnly sworne to vs by the states of that Countrey, being by lawfull and full right now perfectly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15439:5"/> deduolued to our Gouernment; we bended all our carefull thoughts and serious studyes, to deuise what meanes might be inuented, now in the happy entrance of our raigne and soueraignty, to restore our Kingdom, misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly rent &amp; torne with eighteene moneths continual ciuil warre, vnto the splendour of its ancient tranquility; to which purpose we first vndertooke to send vnto the hands of the supreme Burgemaister, before the space of one month should be expired, the Confirmation of all the Priuiledges of that Kingdom, togeather with the Reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salls, of which they seemed so desirous; and withall assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, that peace and publike tranquility should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored, iustice administred, dissentions buried, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall remedies aduised on, in all due and decent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to redresse their agrieuances.</p>
            <p>And although our willfull subiects would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe no answere to this our beneuolent and Roiall offer; yet notwithstanding did we not forbeare no solemne and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique manner to dispatch the Charter of our Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, according to the tenour of that which they had formerly obtained of our predecessour Matthias, their King and Emperour of happy memory, carefully contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and expressing it in iust as many words, clauses, and sentences, as they themselues had heeretofore conceaued and accepted it. And for the more security, we sent by a messenger of our own Chamber, a second Exemplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof to Prage, to be deliuered into the hands of the supreme Burgemaister, and by our gratious and peculiar letters signified so much to all our Barons, Knights, Gentlemen and Cittizens that were there assembled; not being able to perswade our selues, but that by this happy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15439:6"/> occasion of offered peace, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bellious armes, would by performance of their dutifull obedience to their annointed, crowned, and lawful Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, giue vnto the world some noble testimomy of the desire they had to reestablish publique peace, and perfect tranquility.</p>
            <p>But the rufull euent doth pregnantly declare how much they haue deceaued our hopes and expectation. For disesteeming our Royal Charter and Grant of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all their former priuiledges; rashly reiecting the truce, and supension of armes which of our parts, from that tyme we caused to be proclaimed and published; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardlesly neglecting without any answere, our gratious Letters wherin they were mildly and louingely required to send some Agents to conferre with vs about the causes of their discontentes, making them free offer of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct &amp; safeguard of our Royal and inuiolable Word; rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a new and violent commotion in all the body of our Kingdom; leuying new souldiers; soliciting our States of Morauia to participate with them in their rebellion, and treacherous reuolt; wickedly ioyning vnto their troupes all our powers both of horse and foot belonging to that Marquisate; surprizing suddenly our Citty of <hi>Bruna;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiously arresting, and laying their rebellious hands vpon the Captaine and chiefe officers thereof; violently subdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Olmus</hi> the Metropolis and chiefe Citty in that Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; deposing the Magistrats; abolishing the free exercise of sacred religion which in that Metropolitan Church had heertofore bin practized from tyme out of mind; expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all Ecclesiasticall Persons out of their dominions; spoiling, consiscating, and rauishing their goods; solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15439:6"/> religious persons of both sexes most sacrilegiously to violate the sacred bondes of their holy vowes; and finally proscribing, and vnmercifully banishing all such of our noble subiects, as out of their faithfull loyalty to God &amp; Vs, refused to approue and countenance their barbarous and wicked treacheries; they gaue the world apparant testimony how far they were from peaceful cogitations.</p>
            <p>Neither did their audacious impiety containe it selfe heere, but with impetuous violence powred forth the streames of mischiefe to our Arch-Duchy of Austria, where they passed so farre in impudency, that they durst in hostile manner besiege our frontier Towne of <hi>Laa;</hi> and passing ouer the Riuer Dannubius, made their approach vnto our Royall Seate and chiefe Citty of <hi>Vienna,</hi> where discharging their rebellious shot against our Castle, they feared not to leaue to later posterity a hatefull memory of their abhorred Treachery; of which their wicked counsels &amp; most mischieuous attempts what end they might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose vnto themselues, we leaue to others to determine of; and will only adde, that to the complement of this their heap of treasons, when according to custom, and the pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of the Charter, which they call <hi>Bulla Aurea,</hi> we were in person cyted to appeare at Frankford in that most sacred and honourable assembly of the Imperial Electors, as being one of that number, and thereby acknowledged the lawfull and vndoubted King of Bohemia, and Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temuir (or chief vmpyre) of the Empire; they feared not in impudent and shamelesse manner to moue new doubts and vnheard of questions of State; wickedly endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (as much as in them lay) by their seditious libells, to disanull and abrogate the force and prerogatiue of our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15439:7"/> suffrage and session; seeking, cleane contrary both to their duty and our will, to inuolue our naturall and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Subiects in the execrable plots of their hatefull conspiracy: and at that very tyme when the benigne and vniforme consent of our Princes Electours, had iointly raysed vs vnto the highest top of Imperiall Soueraingty, they by a nefarious and vnheard of example of matchlesse perfidiousnes (at whose memory, succeeding posterity will blush with horrour and confusion;) contemning all sacred bondes of their religious Oathes, with earnest en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours sought to frustrate and disauow our Royall Election (as they vainly termed it;) and contrary to the expresse priuiledges of our Kingdome, &amp; inuiolable lawes of our sacred Roman Empire, with their vttermost (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they proued vneffectuall and vaine) labours, in fact sought to transferre our Royall Diademe vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther race and family.</p>
            <p>I need not relate with what secret mines of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheryes, and wicked counsells they laboured to peruert and trouble our Kingdome of Hungary, inducing with their lawlesse trumpets of sedition, our natiue subiects to participate with them in a rebellious and ciuill war; with seuerall sleights inciting Bethlehem Gabor (à sworne Vassall to the Turke) to inuade Cassouia, and conioyning their forces with his, passing againe ouer Danubius by a naual bridge at Presburge, brake into Austria, wasting &amp; forraging the region round about with slaughter, fire, and sword, euen to the walls of our princely Citty of Vienna; exposing to extreme perill and hazard that sacred Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke and Fortresse of the Roman Empire, whose in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, and safe preseruation hath by the Renowned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15439:7"/> German Nation heroically been maintained with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense and profusion of much Christian bloud. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to comprise all in a word, looke what wast, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and mischiefe a sworne enemy can bring vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, all that they most iniuriously and barbarously haue attempted against their lawfull, acknowledged, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued Soueraigne, and his subordinate appointed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrats, neuer prouoked by the least indignity, or iniury of their parts offered them.</p>
            <p>And not being able to extenuate or decline the guilt of these abhominable and enormous crimes, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of new wrongs and iniuryes vnto their former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions and treacheryes; these faithlesse rebells, and their subtile abherents forged a masse of truthlesse calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by which they might seeme, with others like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in disloialty, to blanche and iustify their graceles &amp; outragious proceedings; friuolously carping at our Royal Acceptation, Proclamation, &amp; Coronation; pretending (which yet is horrible to mention) we had vniustly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated our Royall Reuersals, and had condescended to such aggrements and confederacies, as might be deemed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, and preiudiciall to our State and Kingdome. Which slanderous and vntrue defamations, with others of like tenour, wanting all ground of probability, in this tyme and place will need no larger confutation.</p>
            <p>These desperate and inconsiderate beginnings, haue driuen their authours to such height of shamelesse impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, that they make no conscience to infringe and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the very fundamental lawes of their natiue Countrey, making no scruple at once to frustrate the foresayd <hi>Bulla Aurea</hi> of Charles the fourth, the sacred Decree &amp; Sanction
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15439:8"/> of King Vvladislaus, the Reuersalls of the Emperor FER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DINAND, the publique Constitutions and Articles confirmed, and agreed on in the yeare 1547. by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and solemne oath of all the Nobility and state of our Kingdome; hauing withall infringed the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome religiously obserued by al our predecessours, for the tearme of eight whole ages together; seeing that from the raigne of our first Duke Primislaus, in all this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of tyme, no one hath been admitted to the diademe of this kingdome (except Rudolphus, who vnder pretext of hereditary couenants, was raysed to the Scepter, and George Podiebratius) to whom the lineall descent of their Fathers or Mothers bloud, or the happy coniunction and marriage of the daughters of some precedent Kinges, did not bequeath the Crowne and Scepter. And now at last after the deuolution of 270. years they go aboue with cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious questions, &amp; doubtfull cauills to euacuate &amp; delude the Charter, called <hi>Bulla Carolina,</hi> togeather with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the priuiledges therinto inserted by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Frederick the second, iniuriously taxing the noblest and most renowned Emperour, whome for his excellent merits of this Kingdome, our Venerable Predecessours, (much more gratefull then their vngratious ofspringe) did adorne &amp; reuerence with the honorable title of their FATHER &amp; FOVNDER; insinuating in their seditious pamphlets, that this good Emperor in his foresayd decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration did not proceed with candour and good consciēce, but neglecting the tenour of the foresayd <hi>Bulla Aurea</hi> had more regard to the raysing and establishing of his owne issue and posterity, then of the priuiledges of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and for that purpose had aduisedly depraued, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15439:8"/> and impeached the true intent and purport of the same: When not withstanding it is euident, that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd Declaration, being granted with the knowledge and consent of all the Electors of the sacred Roman Empire, and accepted by all the Nobility &amp; States of the Country, was not only precedent to the <hi>goulden Charter,</hi> acted and Concluded at <hi>Norinberge,</hi> but amongst other things, that also was expresly reserued and confirmed.</p>
            <p>Which being so, we could by no meanes be induced to beleeue that any sensible &amp; prudent man could be found out, who had regard of equity and conscience (and much lesse a Prince sprung from the noble German bloud, who by the gracious fauour of God, and great benefite of the sacred Roman Empire had subiects committed to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, to whose iniurious controle he would think it vnfit he should be brought to base subiection) that would vndertake to countenance, cherish, and patronize the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solent rebellion of disloyall subiects, and least of all could we conceaue that any sensed iudgment would be so preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitous &amp; inconsiderate, that without further knowledg of our cause, or more mature examinatiō of the priuiledges of our auncient Imperiall Family; would vnder pretence of a seditious and violent election (frustrate and voide, euen by the letter of the law it self) presume to thrust him selfe into the managing of our publique affayres and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment; but euen in this desperate case an vnhappy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, sutable to the designes of our rebellious subiects, hath not byn wanting: for such an one hath byn found, that cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expectation of almost all the whole Christian world, neglecting the wholsome counsells of the rest of our Princes Electors, hath dared to impale his ambitious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15439:9"/> Head, within the circle of our Royall Crowne; by which it is manifest, that this was the scope and finall end, to which these new Directours from the beginning of their subtile counsels and wicked actions, did chiefly ayme and leuell at.</p>
            <p>But I will heere speake nothing of the disability of their persons, that without al colourable title, durst assume vnto themselues the right of suffrages, &amp; set our Royal Crown vpon the head of a stranger, nothing of the cleare nullity of this their whole new no Election: only I cannot suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently admire, that another Prince, neuer prouoked by vs with the least shaddow of iniury, but rather obliged and bound vnto vs by many respectfull offices of Princelike Beneuolence, should dare to intrude himselfe into the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of our hereditary Kingdome. For what colour could be inuented for him to exact, or accept of a new oath of Homage, and Fealty of our subiects, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious manifestation of their right, either to depose vs or to elect another? Yea, and without all relaxation of their former solemne &amp; religious oaths, by whose sacred bands they yet stand and remaine inuiolably bound to vs: and contrary vnto our lawes and wholsome Constitutions; contrary vnto the publique peace and tranquility of the Empire; contrary vnto all lawes, both humane and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, with a fatall and pernicious example, against al So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Princes (which euermore the very Barbarous Turkes and Tartars haue abhorred and detested) hath vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently sought to exclude vs from our natiue Dominions. But the tyme will come when a seuere and strict accompt of these exorbitant and foule actions will be exacted of him, by the King of Kings, and Iudge of Iudges.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15439:9"/>
            <p>In the meane tyme let him, that being pushed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with heedlesse and intemperate counsells, and spur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on with headlong ambition of vnbridled youth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all care of right or wrong, hath made him self guilty of these haynous and hatefull crimes, for which he neuer can escape the powerfull hand of Gods Iustice and reuenge; let him, I say, consider, how he can iustifie these foule and lawlesse actions to the whole Christian world; how to succeeding posterity; and finally how to the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, frō whence the sublime dignity of the Electorshippe and office of High-Butler is to this Crowne annexed, and of which it doth depēd, as of prime Paramount &amp; Patron; especially knowing that all the Imperiall Electors, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and States of the Countrey, and amongst them the Prince Palatine himselfe, haue solemnely acknowledged Vs for the lawful, proclaimed, crowned, &amp; inuested King of Bohemia; and vnder that title did admit vs to the right of suffrage, in the election of the new King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans; and hauing in the beginning offered his helpful as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance in the friendly treaty of pacificatiō, continued the same, after the Kingdome by right of due succession was deuolued to vs: &amp; when likevvise not long since it seemed good vnto the Princes Electors, assembled at Frankford to resume the foresayd intermitted Treaty, he likevvise cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his letters to that purpose to be vvritten, and by his Agent to be deliuered into our hands, thereby seeming to testify the esteeme he had of Vs, and our Royall Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>Yet least his voide and forcelesse Election, by any meanes, or at any tyme heerafter might prooue preiudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to Vs, the truly, and solemnely annointed King of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15439:10"/> and that we may at once declare openly our Roiall mind in this behalfe; We do protest against all, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular the vniust pretences, that lewdly and wikedly haue bin attempted against vs, and our Imperiall Family; and we namely contradict in all effectuall and most serious manner, which we may, or ought, his vnduely pretended Election, Coronation, and vniust and tyranous vsurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Kingdome, and the Prouinces annexed vnto it; and by our Imperiall and Royall authority do declare them to be voide, frustrate, and of no effect; and by these presents euacuate, disanull, and make them voide, to all intents and purposes: and on the contrary side expresly do reserue vnto our selues, and our Imperiall Family, all fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting remedies, either of right or fact, by way of armes, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments, or confiscations, ordained and established ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ciuil or municipal laws, or by the decrees &amp; consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of our Roman Empire, or Kingdome of Bohemia, religiously protesting, before the Maiesty of our immortall God, that searcheth the secrets of all harts; and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly testifying to the whole farre extended world, with all ensuing posterity; that as there is nothing which hitherto hath sunk into our careful breast more deeply then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that publike tranquility should be restored to our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Prouinces, peaceful security confirmed to our oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed subiects, &amp; that we might entierly recouer that which with violence, iniury, and vniust rebellion hath for a tyme byn treacherously withheld, and forcibly kept from vs, resuming into our hands the Imperial and Royall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which by their faithlesse and treasonable attempts hath hitherto byn most iniuriously oppressed and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: so are we stroken with feeling and deep commisera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15439:10"/> when we recal to mind the wast, slaughter, destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, butcheries, rapines, ruines, combustions, and heape of other woefull miseries, which the necessity of an vnti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely and domesticall warre, raised by the malice of a few rebellious firebrands, and cloked with the specious title of Religion, can bring vpon a multitude of wretched and exhausted subiects; of al which we are most free and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, as hauing performed in ample manner, whatsoeuer may be pretended to be promised in our Reuersalls; and neuer intertained so much as any thought of violating the priuiledges of Religion and maiesty in them graunted: &amp; therfore we returne both the staine, sinne, and shame of these foule and abominable mischeifes vpon the mischei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and guilty heades of their Authors, and first Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuers.</p>
            <p>No lesse seriously protesting that if the vnrestrained fury of our vnbridled souldiers, losing the raines of exact discipline, shall contrary to our martiall law breake out to violent effusion of innocent bloud, and through the outrage of military liberty shall staine themselues with the enormous crimes of theft, rapine, robberies depopulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, incests, adulteries, or the like dreadfull offences; they are all most opposite and contrary to our vpright and mercifull intentions, being audaciously committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the expresse tenour of our Inhibitions: and we will testify how much they do displease vs, by the seuere &amp; ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous chastisement, which vpon iust complaint made to vs, we will cause to be inflicted, not only vpon euery so grieuous and hatefull an offender, but also vpon all and euery such officer of ours, as through his sinnefull conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency, and vniust remissenesse, shall forbeare to execute
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15439:11"/> our seuere and rigorous iustice against so hainous &amp; perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious delinquents.</p>
            <p>But withall we cannot but acknowledge how much it doth concerne vs in conscience and Royall duty, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our Kingdoms, Dominions, and Prouinces from the iniurious oppression of any intruder whatsoeuer: neither shall we need to dread the censures of men, if to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, we shall be inforced to suppresse iniury with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, vniust armes with lawfull power and iust forces, and seeke to quench and extinguish, by all meanes we are able, the flames of rebellion, so fiercely enkindled, and so far extended; to the end we may restore vnto our subiects, who with feare and tyranny are diuorced, and inforcedly drawne from their duty and obedience, the former liberty which they lament and morne to haue lost; that we may lawfully recouer what hath bin vnworthily taken from vs, and with our warlike hand, and if it were needfull; with the profusion &amp; voluntary expense of the last droppe of our dearest bloud, defend &amp; maintaine the rights, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, authority, &amp; Roialties of the sacred Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, &amp; our Imperiall House &amp; Family. We humbly, &amp; in suppliant manner do adore and reuerence the soueraigne Maiesty of our most powerfull &amp; most gratious God, from whose sacred beck &amp; diuine will, all lawfull power &amp; cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding authority is deriued; not doubting, but that we shall find him a faithfull patron, &amp; most iust &amp; seuere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenger of these iniuries, which seeme not so much done vnto vs as to himselfe, whose place &amp; person we represent and beare, &amp; to the whole Christian world. For if this proceeding of rebellious subiects, and patronage of their vnlawfull attempts, should be permitted, no Soueraigne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15439:11"/> Prince could be free from the like insolencies, nor in any security of his estate.</p>
            <p>Wherfore we louingly request all Christian Kings, Princes, and Magistrates, to whome the treacheryes of malecontended subiects against their Superiour, if they should be dissembled or neglected, and much more if they should be patronized, cannot but in consequence yield a most pernicious example: &amp; chiefly vve most benignely and clemently exhort, admonish, and require all the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Princes, &amp; States of our sacred Empire, vvhō this pretended Election, begun and ended against al right and iustice, doth in no meane degree concerne, that in this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and hard enterprise, they would not be displeased, to lend vs cheerfully their carefull labour and helpfull assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</p>
            <p>We likewise interchangeably promising vnto them, all mutuall offices of like beneuolence, the patronage of our Imperiall and Royall protection, togeather vvith the constant and perseuerant preseruation and maintenance of all those wholsome Decrees and Constitutions of the sacred Roman Empire, which may any way concerne the establishment of publique peace and aduauncement of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and piety, and according to the laudable example of our happy &amp; most respected Grandfather and predecessor Ferdinand, sometymes your gratious Emperour, whose name we beare, and who likewise heertofore restored the sacred Empire to tranquillity, when it was tost and shaken vvith stormes of daunger and diuision, not much vnlike to these vvith which it is now againe molested: religiously professing that vve ayme at no other end, then that dissentions, and the harmfull &amp; pernicious seeds of al
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15439:12"/> distrustfull diffidence, may be eternally extirpated and rooted out; and after this long eclypse, the sacred Roman Empire may be restored vnto the lustre and splendour of its auncient concord, glory and power, vvherein it hath confessedly excelled all other Nations. And we haue thought good by these our Letters Pattens to notify thus much to al and singular your Maiesties, Graces, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, that out of our naturall propension &amp; gracious inclination, esteeme our selues eternally obliged vnto you in al mutual offices of due beneuolēce. Dated in our Citty of Vienna the 17. of February anno 1620. and in the first yeare of our Raigne ouer the Roman Empire, our second of Hungary, and third of Bohemia.</p>
            <trailer>By the speciall Command of his Imperiall Maiesty.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15439:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>